A Guide to the John W. Townsend, Jr., Papers, 1949-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
John W. Townsend, Jr., Papers, 1949-1990
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Townsend, John W., Jr. (John William), 1924-2011
Ms1990-068
8.4 Cubic Feet 6 boxes
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The John W. Townsend, Jr., Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1990.
Biographical Note
John W. Townsend, Jr. was born in 1924. He received a B.A. from Williams College in 1947, an M.A. in 1949, and a Sc.D. in 1961. After completing his M.A., Townsent went to work for the Naval Research Labororatory from 1949-1958, spending the last three years as a branch head. In 1958, he moved to NASA for a decade, including three years (1965-1968) as the deputy director fo the Goddard Space Center in Maryland. He left NASA in 1968 to serve as a deputy administrator in the Environmental Sciences Services Administration (1968-1970), and an associate adminstrator for the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (1970-1977). In 1977, he took a break from government work, serving as the president of Fairchild Space and Electronics Company (1977-1982) and, when the company changed names, president of Fairchild Space Company from 1983-1987. In 1987, he returned to NASA as director of the Goddard Space Center until his retirement in 1990. Townsend died in November 2011.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains six boxes of John W. Townsend, Jr.'s personal and professional papers from 1949 until his retirement from corporate and government aerospace work in 1990. In addition to profressional correspondence, memos, and subject files, there are extensive travel files from 1949-1968 and 1985-1990, congressional testimony on NASA projects from 1982-1986, and files on the history of the Upper Air Rocket Research Program at the Naval Research Laboratory from about 1956-1958. Throughout his career, Townsend also served on a number of council, boards, and panels. The collection also includes files from the Thumba Equatorial Rocket Launching Station Advisory Panel (1966-1968, the International Academy of Astronautics (c. 1981-1987), the NASA Advisory Council (1982-1987), the National Academy of Engineering (1982-1987), the National Research Council Space Applications Board (1983-1987), and the Office of Technology Assessment Advisory Board Panel on International Cooperation and Competition in Civilian Space Activities (1982-1985).
Arrangment
The collection is in the original order it was received. For the most part, materials related to the same topic or organization are together and arranged in reverse chronological order.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Archives of American Aerospace Exploration (AAAE); Physics; Science and Technology; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration
Occupations:
Businesspeople; Physicists; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration -- Officials and employees
Contents List
- Goddard Space Flight Center History (3 folders), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
- JWT Reading File (2 folders), 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- JWT Reading File, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- JWT Reading File (2 folders), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
- JWT Reading File (3 folders), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
- JWT Reading File (3 folders), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
- JWT Reading File (2 folders), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
- JWT Reading File (2 folders), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
- JWT Reading File (2 folders), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
- TERLS Advisory Panel (4 folders), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
- Travel JWT, 1949-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Travel JWT, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Travel JWT 1955-1957 (2 folders), 1955-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Travel, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Up to 1957 Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 10)
- JWT Performance Ratings, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- JWT Reading File, 1958-10-23-1958-12-30 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- JWT Reading File, 1959-01-01-1959-03-31 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- JWT Reading File, 1959-04-01-1959-06-30 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- JWT Reading File, 1959-10-01-1959-12-31 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- JWT Reading File, 1959-07-01-1959-09-30 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Travel (2 folders), 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
- Travel Thru 1973 (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
- Rocket Sonde Branch History (2 folders), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
- GARP- Global Atmos. Research Project, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Aerospace America Advisory Board (2 folders), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- American Geophysical Union, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Center for Excellence in Government (2 folders), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
- International Academy of Astro. Committee on Space & Global Change, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- International Academy of Astronautics (3 folders), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
- National Academy of Sciences Nation Weather Observation Systems, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- NASA Advisory Council, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- NASA Advisory Council (2 folders), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
- NASA Advisory Council (3 folders), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
- Earth Observations: Technology, Economics, and International Cooperation, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 18)
- National Academy of Engineering, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- National Academy of Engineering, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- National Academy of Engineering, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- National Academy of Engineering, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- National Academy of Engineering, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- National Academy of Engineering Finance Committee Correspondence, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- National Academy of Engineering Finance Committee, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- National Academy of Engineering Finance Committee, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- National Academy of Engineering Finance Committee, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- National Academy of Engineering Finance Committee, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- National Academy of Engineering Finance Committee, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Travel (2 folders), 1987 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
- Travel (3 folder), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
- Appointment Book, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Appointment Books, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Travel Vouchers (4 folders), 1989 (Box 4, Folder 8-11)
- Travel Vouchers (2 folders), 1990 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
- Memos & Clippings (2 folders), 1990 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
- Memos (3 folders), 1989 (Box 4, Folder 16-18)
- Memos (6 folders), 1988 (Box 4, Folder 19-24)
- Publications, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Space Applications Board -1987 Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- National Resource Council Space Applications Board (NRC SAB) Miscellaneous (4 folders), 1986 (Box 5, Folder 2-5)
- NRC SAB (7 folders), 1985 (Box 5, Folder 6-9, 11-13)
- Minutes of Space Applications Board Meeting, 1985-07-23-1985-07-24 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- NRC SAB (4 folders), 1984 (Box 5, Folder 14-17)
- NRC SAB (4 folders), 1983 (Box 5, Folder 18-21)
- National Research Council Space Science Board, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 22)
- National Research Council Board on Mathmatical Sciences, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 23)
- National Research Council-Commission on Engineer. & Technical Systems, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- National Research Council Commission on Engineering and Technical Systems Meeting, 1985-10-24-1985-10-25 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Committee on NASA Scientific and Technological Program Reviews, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Commission on Engineering and Technical Systems Meeting Briefing Book, 1986-04-17-1986-04-18 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Commision on Engineering and Technical Systems Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 28)
- 1987 Chron File (3 folders), 1987-06-22-1987-12-31 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
- Chronological Correspondence, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- 1986 Chron. Correspondence (4 folders), 1986 (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
- 1985 Chron. Correspondence (2 folders), 1985 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
- National Advisory Committee on Oceans and Atmosphere, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- National Coalition for Science and Technology, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Maryland Academy of Sciences, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Office of Technology Assessment, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Office of Technology Assessment, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Office of Technology Assessment (2 folders), 1983 (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
- Office of Technology Assessment Info. Continued (2 folders), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
- SATSERV (2 folders), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 20-21)
- Testimony-Report "Pioneering the Space Frontier", 1986-07-22 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Testimony-House Committee on Space Science & Applic., 1986-02-27 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Testimony--Shuttle Pricing, 1985-02-21 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Testimony-Wind Shear Detection Technology (2 folders), 1984-07-25 (Box 6, Folder 25-26)
- NRC-Low Level Wind Shear Committee, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Testimony-Space Commercialization, 1984-06-19 (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Testimony-Commercialization of Civil Space Remote Sensing, 1983-06-21 (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Senate Testimony-NOAA Program, 1982-04-21 (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Testimony-U.S. Senate on NASA Applications Program, 1982-03-30 (Box 6, Folder 31)
- NASA Program Management & Procurement Practices/Procedures Testimony, 1981-06-25 (Box 6, Folder 32)